A Guide to the Archives of the Virginia Society of Ornithology, 1929-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Archives of the Virginia Society of Ornithology 1929-2001
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12632
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The collection was a gift from the Virginia Society of Ornithology, through Gene Sattler, to University of Virginia Library on August 1, 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
The organization was founded in 1929 to encourage the systematic study of birds in Virginia, to stimulate interest in birds, and to assist the conservation of wildlife and other natural resources. Activities undertaken by the Society include an annual meeting held in a different part of the state each year, featuring talks on ornithological subjects and field trips to nearby areas; other field trips lasting a day or more and scheduled throughout the year so as to include all seasons and to cover the major physiographic regions of the state; publication of the journal The Raven, a newsletter, and Virginia Birds; study projects such as nesting studies and winter bird population surveys. In addition, local chapters of the Society, located in some of the larger cities and towns of Virginia, conduct their own programs of meetings, field trips, and other projects.
Scope and Content
The Archives of the Virginia Society of Ornithology, 1929-2001, include financial materials, articles of incorporation and papers about its incorporation, by-laws, and tax information. There are also minutes of board meetings, rosters of officers and members, information on local chapters, obituaries of members, general correspondence, information on publications, research projects (such as the Kiptopeke State Park Banding Operation) and research grants. There are 1,638 items in 4 hollinger boxes (1.5 linear feet).
The society shares information about birds and strives to have a positive influence on the preservation of birds and their environment in the Virginia and surrounding mid-Atlantic areas. Some examples of the society's efforts in conservation and environmental issues include their attempts to save Marble Valley near Mason Neck National Wildlife Refuge from a dam that was proposed by Virginia Electric Power Company, opposition to legislation for a landfill in Prince William County (H. R. 664), support for bans on D.D.T., preservation of the Mount Rogers National Recreational Area (at White Top, Virginia), and the prevention of development near national refuge areas, such as the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Park.
Correspondents include officials of the U. S. Forestry Service, the Bureau of Sport Fisheries and Wildlife, the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, members and officers of the Virginia Society of Ornithology, particularly secretary of the VSO, Robert J. Watson and many politicians, including Senator Harry F. Byrd, Jr., former governor, Linwood Holton, Senator William B. Spong, Jr., Thomas N. Downing, Clive L. Duval, Paul Trible, A. Willis Robertson, Edward J. Roberson, William M. Tuck, and Joel T. Broyhill.
The Raven is the main publication for the society. There is correspondence about bird sightings and bird counts for publication in The Raven as well as letters about meeting deadlines and resolving the backlog of issues.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically within each folder.
Contents List
- Articles of Incorporation, amendments, by-laws, and constitution, 1954-1993, 36 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
- Articles of Incorporation: annual reports, and tax exempt status, 1967-1991, 58 items. (Box-folder 1:2)
- Awards for service and conservation, 1973-1987, 5 items. (Box-folder 1:3)
- Board Meeting Minutes, Decisions (also called Executive Committee), 1954-1974, 69 items. (Box-folder 1:4)
- Board Meeting Minutes, Decisions and Resolutions Committee (1932-1935; 1966; 1985), 1975-1990, 31 items. (Box-folder 1:5)
- Correspondence, 1936-1954, 61 items. (Box-folder 1:6)
- Correspondence, 1955-1959, 114 items. (Box-folder 1:7)
- Correspondence, 1960-1964, 98 items. (Box-folder 1:8)
- Correspondence, 1965-1966, 75 items. (Box-folder 2:1)
- Correspondence, 1967-1971, 118 items. (Box-folder 2:2)
- Correspondence, 1972-1982, 118 items. (Box-folder 2:3)
- Correspondence, 1983-1988, 76 items. (Box-folder 2:4)
- Correspondence-Conservation, 1956-1966, 66 items. (Box-folder 2:5)
- Correspondence-Conservation, 1967-1972, 60 items. (Box-folder 2:6)
- Correspondence-Conservation, 1973-1979, 57 items. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Correspondence-Conservation-Assateague Island, 1965, 4 items. (Box-folder 3:1)
- Correspondence-Conservaton-Assateague Island, 1970-1985, 64 items. (Box-folder 3:2)
- Correspondence-Conservation-Back Bay National Wildlife Refuge, 1970-1976, 58 items. (Box-folder 3:3)
- Correspondence about The Raven, 1969-1980, 55 items. (Box-folder 3:4)
  Discussions about the scheduling and backlog of issues.
- Field trips (Forays), 1969-1984, 5 items. (Box-folder 3:5)
- Guidelines for Bird Watching, 1929; 1983-1986, 11 items. (Box-folder 3:6)
  Includes Rare Bird Alert (phone hotline); instructions for How to Lead a Birdwalk; and a directory of lecturers.
- History of the establishment of the Virginia Society of Ornithology, 1929-1931, 24 items. (Box-folder 3:7)
  Founding of the organization and first memberships.
- Local Chapters, 1967-1981, 60 items. (Box-folder 3:8)
- Local Chapter Directories, 1970-1990, 20 items. (Box-folder 3:9)
- Local Chapter Wilson Ornithological Society, 1968-1969, 7 items. (Box-folder 3:10)
- Members Honorary, 1931-1982, 15 items. (Box-folder 4:1)
  Letters and certificates.
- Members Obituaries, 1973; 1983-1984, 5 items. (Box-folder 4:2)
  Includes obituaries for James J. Murray Sr.; James Eike; and Ruskin Freer.
- Membership Lists, 1931-1972, 68 items. (Box-folder 4:3)
  Includes a list of charter members.
- Membership Lists, 1977-1985, 8 items. (Box-folder 4:4)
- Membership Questionnaire, 1987-1988, 23 items. (Box-folder 4:5)
  Feedback from members about the newsletters.
- Officers, 1929-1987, 52 items. (Box-folder 4:6)
- Publications: correspondence about The Annotated Checklist of "Virginia's Birdlife" and Records Committee 1952-1980, 19 items. (Box-folder 4:7)
- Publications Committee Meetings, 1989-1990, 11 items. (Box-folder 4:8)
  Publications meeting minutes about The Raven, Virginia Breeding Bird Atlas and Bluebooks.
- Publications Exchanges, 1930-1969, 22 items. (Box-folder 4:9)
  Includes correspondence with Harry Clemons at the University of Virginia Library.
- Research Committee Reports 1972-1974, 1972-1974, 9 items. (Box-folder 4:10)
  Includes James J. Murray Sr. student research grant.
- Kiptopeke State Park Banding Operation, 1983, 11 items. (Box-folder 4:11)
  Mentions Tom Armour and the Williamsburg Bird Club.
- Treasurer's Reports 1954-2001 (including Audit Committee Reports, Dues and Plans 1967-1969; 1976), 1954-2001, 60 items. (Box-folder 4:12)
- Ledger of daily accounting called Chart of accounts, 1977-1992, 1 item.